That was awesome.
Praise the Lord.
I need to do that.
So, we're continuing on What's in the Name, for We Are His Canvas.
We walked through last week.
And I'm going to give you four words today.
Created in Christ Jesus.
But before we get to the passage, if you'll allow me, I'd like to set it up a little bit.
They always say that you haven't done your job of preaching if you don't apply it by the end.
That you can preach without applying, but if you're going to preach, there has to be some kind of application.
But I want to try to just set the context of application for us, both by Kenny.
If you've ever worked with parents of adoptive children, where the child has had significant trauma, you realize that the traumatic event or events in the life of a newborn, of a very young child, has far-reaching impact across the event.
That when we are born, while we're fully intact as a human, even out of the womb, neurological connections get made.
You know, it's why with, like, language, infants will make just about every sound that you hear throughout the globe.
And those that are reinforced, they make more.
And those that aren't reinforced, they don't make.
And it's why, you know, you, if you read African, you probably can't be African-class.
I don't hear the tones of some more languages.
As an instant, I would have.
And so, but that's true for more than just language.
It's true for so much.
And so, trauma, why is our brain?
There are neurological pathways that are created.
Just that as a loving parent, an instant desperately needs to be celebrated and delighted in.
It's why God built them with eyes that are much bigger in relation to their head than anything else.
I mean, the baby's eyes, you look at their eyes, and you're just like,
And you go, I don't understand how it is, but they perceive it.
And they learn that they're valuable.
And they don't do anything to fly and poke them in.
But they're valuable.
And they, and they dress up and say,
Oh, you look cute.
Oh, look at you.
No, you know.
And, and, and their brain is wired.
But neurological synaptic connections happen.
But the reality is that whether it is the good stuff or the bad stuff, our brain is wired.
And if you read your Bible, you are well aware that we live in a broken way.
We live in a context where there's lots of opportunities to experience brokenness.
In fact, I would argue that, that all of us in some way are broken.
And all of us in some way have received wounds.
And just as that excrementation of being the foster care of a child who was profoundly neglected,
or, or, or the victim of, of some kind of awful assault and treatment as an incident,
and that, and that, and that behavior continues on.
And they don't even understand it.
They don't get it.
That it's fair.
It's just that, that, that, that's the extreme case.
But that reality of wounding in our life is just part of being human.
And my experience in ministry, while I teach theology, I believe in theology, I teach the Bible,
I believe in the Bible, we talk about what, what God does, and who God is,
that many of us live our behavior more out of our place of wounding than we do out of the theology we proclaim.
It's, by the way, it's why the Romans 7 there says that.
So I wanted to talk, just to start a little bit, but, and, so I, I spent, I mean, a decade and a half
working with pastors in climatology, because pastors are some highly traumatized people.
I mean, they, one of the hats they're pastor-wares, their corporate hat, you know, pastors wear lots of hats.
And today I was baptized, and right now I'm a mentor, and a few days ago I was a counselor.
I mean, one of the hats you wear is toxic sponge.
And it's an appropriate hat.
People come, they have toxicity, they have pain, they have hurt, and, and as a, a, a spiritual care giver,
and it's not just pastors, multi-pators do this, um, parents do this, um, but, but pastors do a lot of the counselors do this.
And, and that's appropriate and right, but the reality is that if you don't have a place to scream from it,
toxic sponge out, and clean it, over time it degrades the sponge.
And so, I had the privilege for years, over a decade, of working with pastors who never had a chance to squeeze out their sponge,
and out comes all kinds of toxic sponge, because they didn't deal with it.
And in it we talk about different kinds of wounds.
There's wounds of aggression.
That's where you get what you didn't need.
Get what you didn't deserve.
And in particular, when that wound of aggression comes from an authority figure, a parent, an uncle, a clergy, a doctor, a coach, and we see it in the news all the time.
But it has profound ramifications in the life of the person.
Have you ever been talking with someone, and, and, you misstate something, you forget something, you do something, and it's a level three event, and you get a level nine response?
You ever bring that in?
I mean, do you hear what I'm saying, and you get a concept?
It's often growing out of some kind of wound.
That, this level three event has cracked something inside of me that's been wired in unhealthy ways, in broken ways.
And so, I realized out of this, this, you know, level nine, when it's just a level three.
I was working with, we had a couple of kind of our church, and the gentleman was an amazing guitar player.
Amazing.
And he had abilities to lead and kind of dance from the worship that were, he just, he was anointed, he'd like this, he was good at it.
On his guitar, he would be playing a song, and leading worship, and he would, on the song, and the keyboardist would just like be doing a little noodling to do the transition,
and while he's talking about the next song and helping us entering the worship, he would retune his guitar by ear without even one of his little clicking things down his feet,
and getting a different tune so he could play a different song.
And he was that good.
And he was in my office, and he'd only been there for about three or four weeks, and he wanted to lead our worship, and that's not the way we do it.
The property city is an important part of leadership.
It's his character.
I have a demonstration of character over crime.
And I don't know exactly what I said, but it was a level three event.
It was a level nine event.
And he and his wife was there.
She was calm, but he was reading me the right act, and just really laying into me.
And at some point, my training kicked in like, oh, this is classic transformation.
Some pastor gave him the dirty and the bad act.
Some pastor did something to him.
Last year, a decade ago, three decades ago.
I don't know.
Maybe it's still in the passage.
But he transferred my life on to me.
And out of this, I think the people have taken their head.
You've experienced this.
This typical true furnace.
The second thing is we're in the rules as we're folding.
I'm not getting what you needed.
And again, particularly in early development, you've ever worked with parents who take up a child later.
And every child is different.
Everyone reacts differently.
Things in your eye are different.
It's kind of like blood pressure medication.
You know, it works in this person.
It doesn't work in this person.
You don't know why.
Because people are just different.
People respond differently.
But if you've ever worked with an adopted child who has attachment disorder, you can do everything right as a parent.
You can be over the top everything right.
I mean, still, this wound of resolving, it happened when they were young, and it has input.
So, brain gets my head.
By the way, you know, I said with a child, their eyes are gay, and you really need to lay over them.
It's one of their developmental needs to know that they're loved and safe and secure and cared for and just, you know, the part of the beginning because they're in the room.
Do you know that it's true spiritually as well?
When you get a spiritual new birth, someone who comes new in the face, the church really needs to trust.
Oh, they're so wonderful.
I mean, they need to celebrate it and divide it over it.
And that's why some of us who met the Lord in a legalistic context, where you're brand new to the face, and these legalistic structures require you live like an adult, when you're still spiritually pooping in your pants.
And no one is, I mean, they're not rejoicing over you.
Are you feeling me?
You don't have to agree with me, but are you feeling me?
Okay.
I'm not connecting.
These kinds of, and there's also, there's lots of other rooms, there's event trauma, you get in a car accident, and I actually got into a car accident, it was my fault, from Chicago, and I didn't see it, and I pulled out, and it was really traumatizing, but it's traumatizing, and that is, is three weeks later, I'm in my living room, Chicago, you're close to the road,
and I hear this, and I hear this, and my whole body can't escape, which, I mean, the car is not going to come through the window and hit me on the couch, logically safe, but, okay, it's not, I'm kidding.
This kind of trauma can be both individual, and it can be collective.
I worked with an African-American bishop out of Columbus, Dr. Burns, amazing, amazing man of God, and he was in one of my cohorts as we were working with pastors about the name, someone, and one of the exercises he would do is what you find in the Psalms, they would write a lament, the Psalms are full of lament, and he wrote a lament, and his lament was about,
way back when, when he was marching, when he was caught the king, it was a peaceful march, and the National Guard would call it out, and they got water canyons, and dogs, and released him on it.
Can you imagine the trauma of an authoritarian figure as a collective people, and those kind of things can, not just be an individual, but they can be an effort in the community, and we're going to see this, I'm going to take you to a passage, and you'll see what I'm talking about.
So here again, the rules of responding is, do you just have something to bring to the table?
Okay. The really good thing is that while trauma creates rucks in our brain, and we walk down those pathways without even realizing we're walking down the fly, helping mechanisms as a child become so problematic as an adult, and you realize that a problematic isn't adult, and yet,
you know that your brain is not working here, it's actually creating more problems, but it's what you learned back here. The nice thing is folks, that when God made us, He made us with an elastic brain.
Your brain, you know, everything supernatural has a super part, a natural part. Don't ever try to do the super part. That's God's love.
But don't ever think that you don't have an elastic brain. I like the metaphor of, it's like I'm sailing, and I can't blow the boat across the lake, but if I don't put it to sails, it's not going anywhere.
But putting up the sails doesn't make me go anywhere. Putting up the sails just catches the wind that God saves. And so God saves, He does the people, we do the nature, and it's wonderful that He realized that He was holding a world that was going to fall, that was going to be broken, and things going to come, and people were going to hurt one another, and peoples were going to hurt one another, and He was going to affect the way our brain was made.
But He made us all elastic, because He knew that He was going to send a Redeemer who was going to help rewire our brains to do that image-building, when God doesn't demonstrate the brokenness as much as it did prior to salvation and sanctification.
And by the way, glorification, that will all be going on, but we've got any other ways to do that now, I think. We've got some work in this city, Christ.
Okay. Ephesians 2, verse 10.
Do you remember that I talked about a king being a race king passage last week, if you were there last week, that 1 through 9 is really about individual salvation.
It's about the need for a king. It's about the need for me to get saved, for my grace to be saved, and how it works, and how it does, and what it does.
Do you remember that?
And then I made the comment, and I didn't show you, but I made the comment that 11 through 22 is about collective salvation.
It's about Christ dealing with the collective trauma that He wanted to renew in the church of Jesus Christ, because we are His canvas.
We are His new creation. We are His wonderful display that He is doing.
And then He tells us about this canvas.
His canvas is, and here are the four words for today, created in Christ Jesus.
Let me start with the collective piece, if I can.
So collectively, I'll walk through this fairly quickly.
Corey, are you still here?
You're still here.
Two weeks ago, you used two D's, and you said that Ryan taught you that you always had to use these two D's, and I liked it when I saw it, but I can't remember what they were.
Do you remember the two D's?
Yeah, I dedicated the fantasy.
Well, you said, oh, Ryan taught me the different way you're doing when you preach.
But there are these mechanisms to help people remember things.
That was really great.
Well, the Jews actually had mechanisms as well.
And their mechanisms were a little more elaborate, because most people didn't read, and if they did read, they didn't have access to books.
And so, many of them would remember things, and there are ways that you can remember things.
My kids used to sing this song about all 50 states, and they could literally get them, like, from the northwest to the central order.
I mean, they could plot them all the way around the country with a song.
I guarantee, well, I shouldn't say that, unless you're a homeschool mom, you probably can't do that.
So, I do use something called cryosity.
It's a literary mechanism to show what's important, and you see it all over the Bible.
And I'm going to show you one in Ephesians, chapter 2, and supply into this collective nature of being created in Christ Jesus.
It says, not only are you individually created in Christ Jesus, you, the church, is created in Christ Jesus.
And these words, in Christ Jesus, are really profound.
So, let me take you through it, if I can.
So, if you look at verse 11 through 22, you find this structure where what's brought in in the very beginning is closed out at the end.
So, we call it A and A prime.
And then he brings in B, something important, and you'll see it again down below.
And then C, and then C prime, and then B, and then B prime, and then E, and then E prime.
And eventually, you get to the center, and the center is actually what he's trying to emphasize in the east.
So, the structure that they would be aware of was something that they would see it, they would hear it, they would know it, they'd remember it.
So, I want to unpack this one for you, if I can, but I want to do it in a way that helps us understand this collective nature of our own brokenness that Paul was dealing with back then.
He said, you Gentiles were separated from Christ.
At the end, he's going to talk about you're joined together.
So, you do realize the profound racism that was inherent as you read the New Testament between the Gentiles and the Jews of Hope.
Things get embedded into you as a child when your brain gets wired, and in your community as things get wired.
And you take on these assumptions that you then live out of.
And for a Jew, Gentiles are referred to as what God created as fuel for the fires of life.
It was unlawful for a Jewish person to assist a Gentile woman in childbirth, lest they help another one come into the world.
There were some contexts where you broke outside and you married outside of the Judaism into the Gentile context, and they had a funeral for you.
Even the law says you enter a Gentile home and it renders you uncreed.
And imagine if that's the culture in which you're grown up in.
Now, while most of us probably have not been grown up in that culture relative to Jew and Gentile, maybe some of you have, I don't know, but we do have it here in our country with racism.
It's not happening.
And it's wiring from early on where we have this distrust, this disliked of people who are likely.
I remember I was in my mother's living room and one of her friends, an absolutely delightful lady, I mean, one of the nicest ladies I've ever met.
We're sitting there and our kids are like 8, 9, 10, something like that.
She grew up in Harrisburg, Pennsylvania.
She lived in Harrisburg, Pennsylvania.
In the 60s and 70s, at a time when if you were black, you didn't go in certain neighborhoods, and if you were white, you didn't go in other neighborhoods.
And she's sitting there, she's talking about this man that she had met, and she said, and he's perfect.
And my kids kind of looked at him, and I kind of looked at him.
I said, I'm not grateful for anything, but, I mean, he was really blessed.
She couldn't even hear her things.
And afterwards, my 8-year-old daughter, and my 9-year-old daughter, and my 11-year-old son, when we were alone, said, what was up with that?
Where did that come from?
She couldn't even hear us because this, so.
Imagine Paul is speaking to a saint that has been raised to hate the other, to despise the other.
I want to start a little speaker for you.
It's really hard.
So, do you need to know what the loot is?
There, we've got one.
But, yeah, I told you that I, yeah, yeah, yeah.
You ever eaten, boy?
Have it on your list?
So, in the Philippines, if you're there in the evening, you'll hear people walking up and down the street going,
Balut!
It's a delicacy.
It's something that they love.
It's something they think is absolutely wonderful.
I mean, don't hate it.
It's a duck egg.
It's been gestated 16 days.
And fast-boiled.
So, I'll quickly switch that one.
You get the context.
If I showed that in the Philippines, they would start to salivate, folks.
Your brain's been wired.
Do not like balut.
By the way, Jesus did not heal that part of my wiring yet.
I've had it once.
But people will tell me if I'm coming to their house, anything you don't eat, balut.
If you don't like anything else, I'm good to go.
Okay.
They were separated from Christ, joining together.
Exploders and citizens, later on in the passage, fellow citizens.
Foreigners of the covenant, no longer foreigners.
You can just see this thing going.
Here's the switch.
There's a switch in this passage on both sides.
But now in Christ, and on the back side, consequently.
Once far away, now near.
Who's to the far and near?
I mean, do you see this whole building?
Can you imagine how helpful this would be if you're in oral culture?
To be able to remember what Paul, I mean, you hear it read when you come to Creek on Sunday,
but you don't have one of those to go check it out.
And so you remember it.
Here's our peace.
Making peace and not controlling.
And then you finally get to the place where here's the truck, and I'm going to read the passage.
Please destroy the dividing wall.
And that doesn't sound like that incredible.
But let me read it for you.
If you have your Bible, you can turn to the scenes, chapter 2.
Or turn on your Bible and throw it through it and find it.
And I'm going to start, I think it's, I never wrote it down, like, rather 13, or 14.
So here's the crux, the climate, the heart of what he's saying.
By abolishing in his flesh the hostility, which is a law composed of companions expressed in ordinances,
so that he himself might make the two, one new person.
In this way, establishing peace, that he might reconcile them both in one body to God through the cross.
He's two people who were raised to hate each other.
And he might reconcile them both in one body to God through the cross.
By having put to death the hostility.
Folks, it is the act of Jesus Christ that he supernaturally began the concept of rewiring cultural brains,
cultural milieu, to be one body.
And our part is the natural part in the supernatural.
You'll hear us talk a lot here about spiritual disciplines or means of grace.
About God desires to impart grace to the things that we do.
And so as we begin to move into this collective reality,
we always remember it's what God has done himself.
Jewish religion was a religion of walls.
This is the temple or the tabernacle.
And you know there are all these walls.
If you're a high priest who go into the Holy of Holies once a year,
and a special priest who go in a little square box next to him, the holy place,
only the Levites who go in the bitter box that surrounds them,
and only the men who go in that next box,
and then the women and the Gentiles had to be outside of it.
But in the gospel, when Jesus was crucified,
it says that the veil between the Holy of Holies and the holy place was torn from top to bottom.
God did it.
It tells us that there is a priesthood of all believers,
that it's no longer just the Levites,
but all believers can answer into this holy place.
But then it says in Galatians that either it was either male or female in Christ Jesus,
eliminating that wall that was physical in the temple that they could see of division.
And not only that, but there's no Jew or Gentile.
That all these walls are removed because in Christ there is now a new creation,
created in Christ Jesus.
Christ Jesus has begun the process of rewinding his people
to no longer live the way they used to live,
or they were traumatized to live,
or they experienced in the past.
It's a new person.
Okay.
I'd like to run through the individual really quick.
One, forgive me.
It's Corey's phone.
He talked to him.
I said you were right on the mind.
I kind of, you were, you were,
you asked permission and you took it,
and the next time you can do it again.
Okay, so there's a sense in which,
which we want to behold.
And we recognize that we're broken.
I've seen part of the God-shaped vacuum.
We recognize that we're not all that God wants us to be.
We want to be all that God wants us to be,
and yet you feel it.
And so, most people try to stick things in there.
Some people will use illicit relationships.
They really want to be loved.
They want to be known.
And so, illicit relationships.
It might be an adulterous affair.
It might be a pre-fair, I mean, but it could be other things.
We might, we might stick job in there.
I mean, significance in my job.
I mean, I mean, you ever need to work the whole life?
Any of those who?
Yes.
The work can actually become your God.
You know, in the church, one of our,
two of our favorite things in the church,
and we will actually give pastors raises for these things.
Performance addiction and people-treatening.
We try to, you can even try to stick religion in that place.
And yet we recognize that it never quite fills it up.
It never quite satisfies.
And so, our, our, our hope, whoops.
Our hope is that somehow God makes us whole again.
And folks, God's plan is not to make you whole again.
All right, just get up the way.
Wow, well done.
Wow, good and faithful service.
Because we still see this.
Because you are not, you're not created.
You're not, for we are his canvas, created to be whole again.
But for we are his canvas, created in Christ Jesus.
Paul says that when I am weak, I am strong.
That this in Christ Jesus is the definition of all that we are in the kingdom of God.
We are forgiven in him.
We are holy in him.
We are justified in him.
And the truth here, folks, is not that God removes that place of brokenness,
but that very place of brokenness becomes a docking station for the Lord who's in Christ himself.
But Jesus steps into that place of pain.
And he connects with us.
Those woundings of aggression that made him in the curious.
Those woundings of neglect.
But Jesus says, when you open up that place of pain and that place of hurt for me,
because we are his canvas created in Christ Jesus.
Godless access.
You know, I'll try to just give one more illustration.
I know last time Ryan told me, I said one more illustration, then he gave two.
But I won't do that.
In some ways, it's kind of like walking the tightrope with his big body.
And on the one side, you're loved as you are.
But on the other side, God loves you so much, he wants you to be so much more.
On the one side, you're just belonging.
Like the little ancient.
But anyone who's ever raised an ancient knows you don't want,
if the year five, they're still pooping in their penance,
if the year 12, they're still pooping in their penance,
just probably a copy.
We need to do something.
But God calls us on.
I love Paul in Philippians 3, 9 and then 3, 12 and 3, 9.
It's the righteousness of God.
He's saved.
It's what he does.
But in Psalm 12, he says someone to apprehend the ground of hope
of what God has been handed us forward.
God's just worded us forward.
That means a painting, isn't it?
My saddest moment in parenting.
Well, that was one of my saddest moments.
It was when my daughter came home with a report card.
She had about four A's and two B's.
And I said, oh, this is so good for everything.
Well done, you know, my job.
We're looking at this, it's great.
Tell me about these things.
And she turned to her mother and she said,
I'm not a good enough for you.
Isn't that the behavior you need?
I don't know.
I don't know what it is.
God wants you to be better than I love to just like him.
In fact, that greatness that you need,
if you'll open it to him, he will enter it.
And he will begin the supernatural process
of transforming your weakness in these things.
That besetting sin is probably driven by something
that hurts you way back when you.
If you'll, you know, we try to overcome this thing
by just righting up on it.
And God says, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no.
Someone said to me a long time ago,
God cares less that you sin than why you sin.
If you want to get the root, it's driving a little new.
So I'd like to give you a protocol.
Can we just take a minute?
Can you close your eyes?
I'd like you to ask the Lord in your heart
to identify me.
If there is a broken tooth in you,
it's allowing a besetting footing to take root.
But I'd like to give you a little wound.
I'll add a word to this one.
Some of you have it right away.
Some of you are still wondering.
I encourage you to be able to open up to the Lord
of what he might have missed in you.
Step one is allowing the Lord to identify us.
Step two is welcoming Jesus into that place of wounding.
Invite him.
I've always said he'd join me.
So I can come undone.
Invite him.
This is the cloud object that you've been hiding.
Open it up.
And welcome to make it.
Because you're committed in Christ to you.
Or a candle.
Trained in Christ to you.
And if you can't boil that down to one word over one place for you.
What is that place where you want the Lord to deep the truth to you?
And when you leave together and you're sitting in your head with a pen,
you're just right at the end of one word.
And if that's an incredible world that you've seen me to look and listen this week
to what he might be formally doing for our 15th, one word, one song, one song.
And then at the end of the day, you just go to sleep.
Just pull that part out.
And review your day.
See if the Lord saw that.
If the Lord said something.
If the Lord provided something.
If the Lord was created in Christ Jesus.
Did you see more?